there is a lot of
interest in the distinctions
in practice you know attainments
or identifying with certain attainments
and being able to call yourself a
sotapanna an anagami mm-hmm around
an anagami mm-hmm around
but if you call yourself a sota panel
for example
yet you still suffer
so what i mean yeah it's quite
it's quite normal that people would just
sort of try to
tailor and mold terms and terminologies
to the
basically what they would want them to
mean and be that's just how the mind
works that's where the familiarity with the
that's where the familiarity with the
suitors is necessary because
if you read and see what the buddha
meant by sort of then you realize
okay so these are the qualifications i
said that before i think
when i first read it was i think it was
ayakema she had that paper and saw the party in
she had that paper and saw the party in
the three fetchers
they found online i was still a layman
and he was quite um
well saying that he was watered down
it's an understatement basically she was
saying that
we are already sotapannas because
we all know that rituals are empty
you know bowing to shrine means nothing
we all know that
the buddha was the greatest teacher and
we all know that modern science has
proven that
there is really no substance like a
substance of the self
and i remember thinking that i'm oh
great so i'm sort of under there
but then immediately i thought well from
the suffering point of view
and being free from suffering free from
liability to suffering what difference
does it make then and then you realize
that type of sota panna makes no
difference which then means that's not party
which then means that's not party
because the buddha had said what other
part is four noble truths and freedom from
is four noble truths and freedom from
suffering seven grains of sand left
in comparison to the mountain of
suffering destroyed so
yeah you can call yourself whatever you
want but the reality is
do you are you still liable to suffer
are you still liable to not knowing
escape from there is a suffering
internally are you still moved by the
duke afraid of dukkha
if the answer is yes if the answer is i
don't know if the answer is maybe
means you are which means you're not a
certified so that's why you often keep insisting
so that's why you often keep insisting
on that clear
division
and you're saying also that from a
protogenius point of view
the sodium is like in arahant yes yeah
that's right exactly
yeah yeah because if you as a pathogen
think you are practicing the dhamma
means you're implying that you know what
dhamma is
yet the buddha said the knowledge of
what dhamma is begins with
so you can't have it both ways so you
either don't know what dhamma is means
you're not a sort of owner
or you know what dumb is means you're
suddenly but you can't say i'm not a
sotapanna and i know what dhamma is
which is a reference point to the
efforts in my practice
that's how i know i'm progressing so
it doesn't mean that whatever you do is
wrong but means that can only be known
as right in hindsight
after you get the right view after you
become a sort of one
like the simile i told you before
imagine you are in prison all it matters
is whether you're imprisoned
or you're free you're escaped
so the efforts you do in prison towards
the escape
will be the efforts of escape only after
you escaped
because if you haven't escaped even if
you spend 20 years digging a tunnel
you're still prisoner
so that's the point here like not that
your efforts are
useless but unless you're assaulted they
are useless
because you haven't escaped
when your life comes to the end it's not
measured by
like you know what's waiting for you
it's not measured by how hard you tried
or whether you tried or not it's mad
it's measured whether you escaped
or not and say when you know if the gods
catch you or you die before you escaped
the prison no all of your efforts
basically was useless because you
remained a prisoner so that's what i mean when we
a prisoner so that's what i mean when we
insist on this black and white division
but when i insist on the black and white
division is so that you will always
maintain the context of the goal where it matters
the context of the goal where it matters
because it doesn't matter if you thinned
out the wall of the prison
this much or this much what matters is
on which side of the wall you
are because if you die even if there is
just one inch of war left
well you die the prisoner which means
now you're done
because you are on a limited time you're
not going to live forever
and not your every next rebirth will
head towards nibana who knows
and more likely than not he won't so the
chance you have now
to be aware of the possibilities of
escape and the effort towards the escape
to make
is it's a limited time as i said the
gods might just bust in and catch you
and you're done and they'll move you to
another prison
but you're trying or ignoring the fact
that you're still a prisoner
so that you can kind of give more value
to your efforts of escape
is a foolish thing to do because you
have no reference of the escape you
might have been digging the wall for 20
years practicing the dhamma but you don't know
practicing the dhamma but you don't know
if there is another 200 meters of that
wall you don't know because you haven't
escaped so it's wishful thinking to think that
so it's wishful thinking to think that
without having escaped the prison
your efforts are bringing you closer to
the escape
only once you escape the prison when you
look back you can see
yes such and such effort brought me
closer to this cape and hence i
escaped but until you escaped you don't
wanna you should not be entertaining the
notion of
i am closer to the escape because you
might not be and you don't know whether
you are or not
as simple as that and that's exactly the
tujina sort of
note that everything putujna does is
wrong but until he becomes a sort of
runner he should pretty much regard everything
he should pretty much regard everything
with a pinch of salt and as might be
wrong or insufficient
and it's again you don't lose anything
by the way
except maybe a bit of your complacency
if you keep that in mind that only
escape matters
that's the ultimate goal so it's going
to be more unpleasant to you
to maintain that context but because of
that unpleasant context
you will have the direction to strive
for the measure to achieve
but if you say oh well that's you know
tall order
all it matters is trying your best
that's just what prisoner will tell
himself who is aware that he's still a prisoner
who is aware that he's still a prisoner
and he cannot bear that reality so then
he just
tries to mask it and make it more of
that which it isn't
it's not it oh it doesn't matter no it
matches the escape matters if it doesn't
matter you wouldn't have tried to escape
in the first place
if becoming a sword upon it doesn't
matter you wouldn't have even read the
sutas and try to practice
it if they escape from suffering doesn't
matter you wouldn't have been doing this
you wouldn't have been doing this
already you wouldn't be saying that it
doesn't matter
because you know that it matters
so yeah it's black and white very black
and white
and it's it's good for you to think that
it's black and white because if you
start making it gray
exactly you'll be a complacent prisoner
who likes to think that he's
getting there with the escape but in
reality he has no idea how much of that
wall is left for him to dig
and whether he's going to get caught or
not and be sent to a dungeon or
something where he cannot dig through
yes plenty of time yeah everything it's
tied with that notion of basically
forgetting that you are
on a border time and your practice now
unless has passed that threshold of soda
party as the buddha would say
unless you pass the threshold soda party
no amount of your practice then is
guaranteed they will be picked up and taken again
they will be picked up and taken again
you have no idea because you might spend
euns in the realm that will be completely
in the realm that will be completely
unsuitable for
any practice of dharma so from the point
of view of eons
of actions performed in the realms that
are completely against the dharma 20
years of your practice and meditation
is nothing nothing so
keep that in mind and donald's
perspective and
don't try and water down the threshold
of success which is sort of party that's
where we'll say
basically sold upon ohio is the only
ones that should not be fearing
rebirth and what's next because at most
they have a limited time
before they fully free their mind
so it's again it's a win-win the only
thing you lose is complacency here and
now
so if you're making effort great and
also think of this as a threshold
even better you're going to make twice
as much effort
but if you try to argue against this
point it's only because you want to
compensate for the lack of effort or basically try
for the lack of effort or basically try
to pretend
that you somehow know what the escape is
while simultaneously admitting
that you haven't escaped you hope they
escape exactly you you you it's it's too
exactly you you you it's it's too
unpleasant to admit
that you are a prisoner
but that's kind of the necessary step
because that will then make you really
want to escape